Guide to the Jean-Pierre Faure Collection on Raymond Queneau and Pataphysics
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Jean-Pierre Faure collection on Raymond Queneau and pataphysics
1901-2003
1950-2000
GEN MSS 1010
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
1.33
(5 boxes) + 1 art, 2 record album storage
Collection consists of correspondence and printed and other materials relating to Raymond Queneau and the Collège de 'Pataphysique. There are separate correspondence files for Queneau and Jean-Pierre Faure from members of the Collège de 'Pataphysique and others. The bulk of the correspondence to Queneau, received during his tenure with the Collège as "Transcendental Satrap" from the early 1950s to early 1970s, is from Jean-Hugues Sainmont, pseudonym of Emmanuel Peillet. Other correspondents include Henri Bouché, Jean Ferry, Raymond Fleury, Thiéri Foulc, and bookseller Syvain Goudemare. In addition to these larger files, there is one autograph postcard signed from Alfred Jarry to Gustave Kahn. Printed ephemera, relating chiefly to the Collège de 'Pataphysique, includes clippings, postcards, documents, circulars, manifestos, publicity, catalogs, and a diploma, by the Ordre de la grande gidouille, awarded to Queneau. Audiovisual material includes photographs of Sainmont, Bouché, Baron Jean Mollet, Boris Vian, and Henri Robillot, among others, and several record albums and one audiocassette.
Faure, Jean-Pierre
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Librarie Benoit Forgeot on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund, 2010.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Box 7 contains (audiovisual material): Restricted fragile. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
Associated Materials
Printed monographs removed from the collection are cataloged separately.
Raymond Queneau (1903-1976)
Raymond Queneau, French novelist and poet, was born in Le Havre to Auguste Queneau, a businessman, and Josephine Mignot. After completing his studies at the lycée in Le Havre, Queneau went on to the University of Paris in 1920 and took his degree in philosophy in 1926. That same year he was called to military duty in Algeria and Morocco. A year later he returned to Paris, where he married Janine Kahn, with whom he had a son, Jean-Marie, in 1934. Queneau worked odd jobs for ten years before becoming a reader at the Gallimard publishing house in 1938. Queneau's editorial career was interrupted briefly when he was drafted into the military in August, 1939. Serving in small provincial towns, he was promoted to corporal just before being demobilized in July, 1940. Queneau then returned to Paris and, in addition to his editorial duties at Gallimard, where he became general secretary, he collaborated on clandestine publications and wrote a column for Front National until 1945. Queneau remained at Gallimard for the rest of his life and, in addition to his editorial work and publications, he was a member of the Collège de 'Pataphysique.
Biographical information taken from Slomski, Genevieve. "Raymond Queneau." Cyclopedia of World Authors, Fourth Revised Edition (2003): 1. Biography Reference Center. Web. 7 October 2013.
Collège de 'Pataphysics
The Collège de 'Pataphysics, founded in Paris in 1948, is a society dedicated to the "science of imaginary solutions" developed by Alfred Jarry in the character of Doctor Faustroll in Gestes et opinions du Docteur Faustroll, pataphysicien (Paris: Eugène Fasquelle, 1911).
Jean-Pierre Faure
Jean-Pierre Faure is a collector and bookseller based in Paris and member of the Collège de 'Pataphysique. Faure owns the bookstore "Un regarde moderne," which has served as the central distributor for the "graphzine" movement since the 1980s.
Scope and Contents
Collection consists of correspondence, printed ephemera, photographs, sound recordings, and other material relating chiefly to Raymond Queneau and the Collège de 'Pataphysique. There are separate correspondence files for Queneau and Jean-Pierre Faure from members of the Collège de 'Pataphysique and others. The bulk of the correspondence to Queneau, received during his tenure with the Collège as "Transcendental Satrap" from the early 1950s to early 1970s, is from Jean-Hugues Sainmont, pseudonym of Emmanuel Peillet. Other correspondents include Henri Bouché, Jean Ferry, Raymond Fleury, Thiéri Foulc, and bookseller Sylvain Goudemare, with materials mentioning Alfred Jarry, Baron Jean Mollet, Boris Vian, and Noël Arnaud. In addition to these larger files, there is one autograph postcard signed from Alfred Jarry to Gustave Kahn.
Printed ephemera, relating chiefly to the Collège de 'Pataphysique, includes clippings, postcards, documents, circulars, manifestos, publicity, catalogs, and a diploma, by the Ordre de la grande gidouille, completed in manuscript and awarded to Queneau. Other material in the collection includes photographs of Sainmont, Bouché, Mollet, Vian, Henri Robillot, and other members of the Collège, as well as several record albums and one audiocassette.
Arrangement
Organized into three series: I. Correpondence, 1901-2003. II. Printed and Other Material, 1946-2002. III. Audio Recordings, 1956-1960.
Authors, French -- 20th Century; French literature -- 20th Century; Pataphysics; Audiocassettes; Audiovisual materials; Long-playing records; Photographic prints; Sound recordings; Authors -- France -- 20th Century; Arnaud, Noël, 1919-2003; Bouché, Henri; Boullet, Jean, 1921-1970; Faure, Jean-Pierre; Ferry, Jean, 1906-1974; Fleury, Raymond; Foulc, Thiéri; Goudemare, Sylvain; Jarry, Alfred, 1873-1907; Kahn, Gustave, 1859-1936; Mollet, Jean, baron; Queneau, Raymond, 1903-1976; Robillot, Henri; Sainmont, Jean-Hugues, 1914-1973; Vian, Boris, 1920-1959; Collège de 'pataphysique; Ordre de la grande gidouille
- Correspondence, 1901-2003; Series I; 0.42; (1 box)
  Arrangement
  Arranged chonologically within files.
  Scope and Contents
  Series I. contains separate files for Raymond Queneau and Jean-Pierre Faure correspondence from the Collège de 'Pataphysique. The bulk of the correspondence to Queneau, received during his tenure with the Collège as "Transcendental Satrap" from the early 1950s through early 1970s, is from Jean-Hugues Sainmont, pseudonym of Emmanuel Peillet; most of the correspondence is also signed by Sainmont with another pseudonym ("Latis"). Other correspondents include Henri Bouché, Jean Ferry, Raymond Fleury, Thiéri Foulc, and later, to Faure, bookseller Sylvain Goudemare. Material also mentions Alfred Jarry, Baron Jean Mollet, Boris Vian, and Noël Arnaud.
  In addition to these larger files, there is one autograph manuscript postcard signed from Alfred Jarry to Gustave Kahn.
  - Raymond Queneau correspondence, 1950-1999, undated; 8 (Box 1)
    Includes one TL, corrected, from Queneau to "Daubercies," dated 1961, and third-party correspondence
  - Jean-Pierre Faure correspondence, 1990-2003, undated; 3 (Box 1)
  - Empty folders, undated (Box 1)
  - Postcard from Alfred Jarry to Kustave Kahn, 1901 April (Box 1)
- Printed and Other Material, 1946-2002; Series II; 0.63; (2 boxes) + 1 art object
  Arranged alphabetically by material type and/or title.
  Series II. contains printed ephemera, manuscript material, and photographs relating chiefly to the Collège de 'Pataphysique. Printed ephemera includes clippings, postcards, circulars, manifestos, publicity, catalogs, documents, and a diploma, by the Ordre de la grande gidouille, awarded to Queneau. There are photographs of Jean-Hugues Sainmont, Henri Bouché, Baron Jean Mollet, Henri Robillot, Boris Vian, and other members of the Collège.
  - Diploma, "Ordre de la grande gidouille", 1950 (Box 2 (Art))
  - Empty envelopes, 1989-2002, undated; 2 (Box 3)
  - Manuscript material, undated (Box 3)
  - Photographs, 1946-1972, undated; 2 (Box 3)
  - Pin with Ubu and Collège de 'Pataphysique symbol, undated (Box 3)
  - Plant specimen, undated (Box 3)
  - Printed ephemera (clippings), 1947-1959, undated (Box 3)
  - Printed ephemera (postcards), undated; 2 (Box 3)
  - Printed ephemera (other), circa 1950-2000; 5 (Box 4)
- Audio Recordings, 1956-1960; Series III; 0.21; (1 box)
  Conditions Governing Access
  Box 7: (audiovisual material): Restricted fragile. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information
  Arranged alphabetically by title.
  Series III. audio recordings include commercial reproductions of work by Boris Vian and music and songs to a 1958 Théâtre National Populaire production of Alfred Jarry's Ubu.
  - "Alias Henry Cording and His Original Rock and Roll Boys" by Henri Salvador, 10" record album, 1956 (Box 5 (Record album storage))
  - "Chansons 'possibles' et 'impossibles'," 10" record album, 1956 (Box 6 (Record album storage))
  - "Chansons possibles" by Boris Vian, 7" record album, 1956 (Box 7)
  - "Homage à Luc Etienne" (audiocassette), 1990 May 16; 1 (Box 7, Item barcode 39002109979808)
    Audiovisual material. Restricted fragile. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
  - "Musique et chansons pour Ubu," 7" record album, circa 1958 (Box 7)
  - "Pierre Brasseur" by Boris Vian, 7" record album, 1960 (Box 7)
- Oversize, 0.08; (1 box)
  - Manuscript material (In Series II), undated (Box 8)
  - Photographs of Boris Vian (In Series II), undated; 3 (Box 8)
  - Printed ephemera (clippings) (In Series II), 1947-1957, undated (Box 8)
  - Printed ephemera (other) (In Series II), 1984, undated (Box 8)